<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Machiuells dogge</title>
            <author>Breton, Nicholas, 1545?-1626?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16756</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3664.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109778</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845423</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845423</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10320</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16756)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10320)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 894:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Machiuells dogge</title>
                  <author>Breton, Nicholas, 1545?-1626?</author>
                  <author>Breton, Nicholas, 1545?-1626? I would, and would not. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Barnard Alsop for Richard Higgenbotham, and are to be solde at his shop at the signe of the Cardinals Hatte, neere S. Sepulchres Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Nicholas Breton.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ (-E4).</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Reprints 20 stanzas from Breton's "I would, and would not".</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 17169 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:10320:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10320:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>MACHIVELS <hi>DOGGE.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>MY d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gged Muſe where haſt thou dwelt ſo long,</l>
               <l>Or hid thy ſelfe from this ſad heart of mine?</l>
               <l>That longs to heare ther ſing that deadly ſong.</l>
               <l>That Sorrow ſet vnto that ſoule of thine?</l>
               <l>Where tyred ſpirits, that in torments dwell,</l>
               <l>Finde how the Deuill turnes the world to hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Doeſt thou not ſee, except thou wilt be blinde,</l>
               <l>How life hath loſt the notes of natures loue:</l>
               <l>And wiſdomes wordes are helde but as a wind,</l>
               <l>Where Machauilians ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chleſſe villaines proue,</l>
               <l>And Tigres, Foxes, wolues and Owles, and Apes,</l>
               <l>Beganne the world in ſhewes of humane ſhapes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Say truth good dogge, and doe not ſpare to barke,</l>
               <l>But ſnarle and ſnappe at euery ſnea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing thiefe.</l>
               <l>Let not a Curre goe lee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the darke,</l>
               <l>But ſhew thy kind, bough <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a dogge be briefe;</l>
               <l>Lie at the doore, giue wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> houſe,</l>
               <l>Scratch out a flea and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:2"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tudy no termes of ſtayned Eloquence,</l>
               <l>But ſpeake as plainely, as a paued floore:</l>
               <l>Giue pride the height of ſinnes preheminence:</l>
               <l>And bid the Pander keepe the Lechers doore:</l>
               <l>And let the flatterer bee the Slingthrifts gueſt,</l>
               <l>And locke the Miſers heart vp in his cheſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Briſſell thy ſelfe vp at a beaſtly ſlaue,</l>
               <l>That cares for nothing, but to feede on fat:</l>
               <l>And caſt a leere at ſuch a lurking knaue,</l>
               <l>As pries about thee like a prowling Cat:</l>
               <l>And if the Foxe come neere thy Chickens penne,</l>
               <l>Runne at the Roague, and courſe him to his denne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But if thou chance to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Lyon roare,</l>
               <l>Lie downe and cowch, there is no looking out:</l>
               <l>But if thou meetſt a Bull or a wilde Bore,</l>
               <l>Beware the horne, and come not neere the ſnowte:</l>
               <l>For other Cattell, horſe, or Mare, or Aſſe,</l>
               <l>Come not too neere their heeles, and let them paſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Be plaine and honeſt, doe not ſweare and lie,</l>
               <l>Nor complement with cappe, and crouch and knee,</l>
               <l>Nor like a Baby runne away and crie,</l>
               <l>For feare to looke vpon a Humble Bee:</l>
               <l>Loue no extremes in neyther heate nor colde,</l>
               <l>And make no treaſure of ill gotten golde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:2"/>
               <l>Doe not perſwade a foule ill fauourd ſlut:</l>
               <l>Shee is as fayre as <hi>Venus</hi> forehead cloth:</l>
               <l>Nor ſtand to teach a Sparrow to keepe Cut:</l>
               <l>Nor dwell all day vpon a diſh of broth:</l>
               <l>But doe thy buſineſſe that thou art about,</l>
               <l>And when tis midnight put the candle out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Stand, ſtrut and ſtout, and doe not wagge the tayle</l>
               <l>At euery fillip of a fidling friend,</l>
               <l>Barke at a Cowe that kicketh downe her paile,</l>
               <l>And make no banquet of a puddings end:</l>
               <l>Call not a knaue a knight, nor clowne a king,</l>
               <l>In rules of reaſon, tis a raſcall thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For birdes, let not the Crane picke out thine eyes,</l>
               <l>Nor let the Parat teach thee how to prate:</l>
               <l>Nor fill thy paunch too full of Woodcockes pies,</l>
               <l>Nor let Madge Howlat make thee watch too late:</l>
               <l>Nor let the Cuckoe teach thee how to ſing,</l>
               <l>Nor with the Buzard, make too low a wing,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For Fiſhes doe not ſwallow like the Whale;</l>
               <l>Nor like a Cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fiſh creepe into a hole:</l>
               <l>Learne of the Dolphin how to keepe his ſcale,</l>
               <l>But doe not ſwim among the Herrings ſhole:</l>
               <l>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ie of the Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oke to ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, but with the floud,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:3"/>
               <l>But whether runneſt thou Counter with thy ſent,</l>
               <l>Backe take the wind, and beat it out againe:</l>
               <l>The Hare is gone, thou knoweſt not where ſhee went,</l>
               <l>Liſt, how the hounds doe plie it on the plaine,</l>
               <l>Well fare the kennell makes the merry eye,</l>
               <l>Hah, good olde <hi>Tibbe,</hi> tis pitty thou ſhouldſt die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But leaue this hunting, let vs fall to play</l>
               <l>At Cardes or Dice, or ſome ſuch prety ſport.</l>
               <l>With merrcy trickes to paſſe the time away.</l>
               <l>While idle ſpirits doe but long and ſhort,</l>
               <l>But ſo, that in the end we may finde out,</l>
               <l>How Gamſters bring their golden world about.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Take vp the Cardes, and giue the Coates their places,</l>
               <l>Honour the Kings, bee ſubiect to their ſwordes,</l>
               <l>Bow to the Queenes, doe reuerence to their Graces,</l>
               <l>But vſe the Knaues, but as the time affoordes:</l>
               <l>Where, rhough the knaue of Clubs be calde the chiefe,</l>
               <l>An other knaue may be as cloſe a thiefe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sort out the ſuites, together lay the Trickes,</l>
               <l>Note a Bumcarde, and how to ſtoppe at neede,</l>
               <l>The Harts are ſpotted, Diamonds are but prickes,</l>
               <l>His time ill ſpent, that happens beſt to ſpeed.</l>
               <l>The Spades are broken, and the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rotten,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd by the ſmall Cardes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:3"/>
               <l>But what ſhall bee our game? Primero? Gleeke?</l>
               <l>Or one and thirty, Bone ace, or new Cut,</l>
               <l>Or Mawe, or Ruffe, or Trumpe, what doe you leeke?</l>
               <l>Or Poſt and Paire, or put and vnder put:</l>
               <l>All one to me, no Carde can come acroſſe:</l>
               <l>Who hath no money, hath no feare of loſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But let vs thinke vpon a gallant game,</l>
               <l>Primero? yea, there let vs ſet our reſt:</l>
               <l>Prime in his nature hath a Princely name:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Hero</hi> beares his honour with the beſt,</l>
               <l>Oh royall grounds that ſuch a game begunne,</l>
               <l>Bleſt be the Fathers chriſtendo ſuch a ſonne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But it is coſtly to apply this play?</l>
               <l>A good aduenture ſhewes no idle vaine:</l>
               <l>For when the ſtake is at the loweſt ſtay,</l>
               <l>A happie Prime will make all whole againe,</l>
               <l>Then deale the Cardes, and happy be his time,</l>
               <l>That ſets his fortune on ſo fayre a Prime.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Enough of this, now let vs goe to Gleeke:</l>
               <l>Fayre play, and ſquare, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haue no falling out.</l>
               <l>Looke to your hand, and haue no braines to ſeeke:</l>
               <l>For dotage often comes home with a flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ion make,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:4"/>
               <l>But let mee ſee, who ſpeakes vnto the Ruffe?</l>
               <l>Who vies it? he that hath the happieſt ſuit:</l>
               <l>But packe no Cardes, for that deſerues the cuffe,</l>
               <l>And euer let the ſtanders by bee mute:</l>
               <l>For many a time, a blinde and ſimple eye,</l>
               <l>May looſe much money by the ſtanders by.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But deale the cardes, a mournivall of Aces,</l>
               <l>Welcome poore ſpots that makes the Players rich,</l>
               <l>And better welcome then thoſe painted faces,</l>
               <l>That lay a Lordſhip in a durty ditch:</l>
               <l>But what? are all the ſtakes vp? then away,</l>
               <l>And let vs fall vpon ſome other play.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Giue ouer Gleeke, a ſet or two at Maw:</l>
               <l>The Knaue fiue fingers, and the Ace of Harts:</l>
               <l>It was a Clowne that firſt deui'ſd the law,</l>
               <l>That Peſants ſo ſhould come to play their parts,</l>
               <l>And baſeneſſe ſo about the Game ſhould bring,</l>
               <l>A knaue ſhould take the ſtake vp from the king.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And truth to tell, I cannot well diſgeſt,</l>
               <l>Theſe heaues and helpes, and liuings after loſſe,</l>
               <l>For when the game ſometimes is at the beſt,</l>
               <l>A baggage carde may hap to come a croſſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd make the Gamſter fret, and ſweare and curſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> leaue him neuer a penny i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:4"/>
               <l>Then let vs leaue this Mawe, and goe to R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffe,</l>
               <l>Honour the King, the Queene, and the Knaue too:</l>
               <l>But yet mee ſeemes it ſmelles of Countrey ſtuffe,</l>
               <l>A Knight, vnto a Knaue ſhould honour doe,</l>
               <l>Yet, if the Cardes ſuch fortune him allot,</l>
               <l>If that it be his due, denie him not.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But, for I ſee, ſome hidden note doth reſt,</l>
               <l>Of baſe Ambition in a Peaſants pride:</l>
               <l>To giue a Knaue ſuch honour though in ieſt,</l>
               <l>I meane at Cardes, when Trompe is on his ſide,</l>
               <l>Caſt vp the Cardes, the Trickes together put:</l>
               <l>And leauing Ruffe, lets fall vpon New Cut.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>New Cut, indeede, lets ſee no iugling Cut,</l>
               <l>But he that hits the game vpon the head,</l>
               <l>May in his bagge the money cloſely put,</l>
               <l>While other Gamſters may goe bare to bed:</l>
               <l>But, whatſoeuer Carde you play vpon,</l>
               <l>Take heede of going out, for then all's gone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So farewell New Cut, and to bee you pleaſde,</l>
               <l>A prety game to get into the hole:</l>
               <l>Looſe a good Carde, and by an Ace bee eaſde,</l>
               <l>A lingring ſport, the laſt man winnes the gole:</l>
               <l>A prety note, for many an eye to make,</l>
               <l>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> holdes out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:5"/>
               <l>But leauing Cardes, lett's goe to dice awhile,</l>
               <l>To Paſſage, Treitrippe, Hazarde or Mumchaunce:</l>
               <l>But ſubtill Mates vvill ſimple mindes beguile:</l>
               <l>And blinde their eyes with many a blincking glaunce:</l>
               <l>Oh, cogges and ſtoppes, and ſuch like diueliſh trickes,</l>
               <l>Full many a purſe of golde and ſiluer pickes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And therefore firſt, for hazard, hee that liſt,</l>
               <l>And paſſeth not, puts many to a blancke:</l>
               <l>And trippe without a Treye makes had I wiſt</l>
               <l>To ſitte and mourne among the ſleepers ranke.</l>
               <l>And for Mum-chance, how ere the chance doe fall,</l>
               <l>You muſt be mum for feare of marring all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſince I ſee that both at Cardes and Dice,</l>
               <l>There is ſuch cogging, ſtopping, cutting, ſtriking,</l>
               <l>Where poore Repentance payes ſo deare a prize,</l>
               <l>For want of wit, in idle wantons liking:</l>
               <l>I care not, if I quite giue ouer play:</l>
               <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et my wits to worke ſome other way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then let vs goe to gardning, planting ſowing,</l>
               <l>And turning vp of paſture grounds for graine:</l>
               <l>But in ſowle weather hearbes may haue ill growing,</l>
               <l>And in fat groundes, ill weedes grow vp amaine,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd many a time doth many a poore man furde</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eld of corne all blaſted with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:5"/>
               <l>Then leaue the Plough, and take the Merchants trade,</l>
               <l>And ſet our fortunes vpon ebbes and floods;</l>
               <l>Alas, a poore colde reckening will bee made,</l>
               <l>When Seas or Pirats ſwallow vp the goods,</l>
               <l>And hee that ſets his ſtate vpon a winde,</l>
               <l>May looke before, and ſee his haps behind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What? ſhall we then be Lawyers? out alas,</l>
               <l>It is a fearefull clogge of conſcience,</l>
               <l>To ſee a poore man from his right to paſſe,</l>
               <l>When in the proofe of truthes experience,</l>
               <l>A quitidy, a quirke, a word, a point,</l>
               <l>May put a long ioyed title out of ioynt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shall wee be Souldiers then? but, to what end?</l>
               <l>Vnchriſtian comfort is the fruit of blood:</l>
               <l>Better keepe inward with a faithfull friend,</l>
               <l>Then purchaſe foes for any priuate good:</l>
               <l>And better pray that quarrels all may ceaſe,</l>
               <l>And ſay, God ſaue the holders vp of peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What? ſhall wee then be Gallants? and go gaye?</l>
               <l>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue eaſily, feede, and ſit, and ſleepe or talke,</l>
               <l>Or ſtudy, how to throw our wealth away?</l>
               <l>Or with a wanton make an idle walke?</l>
               <l>No, thinke vpon the Prouerbe often tolde,</l>
               <l>A careleſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:6"/>
               <l>What? ſhall wee then be Scholars? plie our bookes?</l>
               <l>Alas, poore learning hath but little Grace:</l>
               <l>And, wee that want the golde and ſiluer hookes,</l>
               <l>Shall hardly hit vpon a happy place,</l>
               <l>Yet let vs loue all holy heauenly lines,</l>
               <l>And wiſh them honour that are true Diuines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What? ſhall wee then be men of Art and Skill,</l>
               <l>And by our Phiſicke to preferments clime?</l>
               <l>No, a miſtaken or diſtempered pill,</l>
               <l>May bring a man to death before his time,</l>
               <l>Yet, let vs loue all Noble Studients</l>
               <l>That cure, but doe not kill their Patients.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What? ſhall wee then goe learne to play and ſing,</l>
               <l>And ſtudy Muſicke in a merty Note?</l>
               <l>No, heauy ſtraines doe come from that hearts ſtring,</l>
               <l>That makes a liuing of a Liuery coat:</l>
               <l>Yet, let vs loue thoſe Angelike ſweet voyces,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſiluer ſoundes, the ſorry heart reioyces.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What? ſhall wee then become cloſe Alkemiſts,</l>
               <l>And ſtudy the Philoſophers faire ſtone?</l>
               <l>Oh no, I ſee a ſight of had I wiſts,</l>
               <l>Doe weepe for ſiluer when their gold is gone:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ope Noddy, neuer was there ſuch an other,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> make a Coſen of a ſimple brother.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:6"/>
               <l>What ſhall we then doe? ſomewhat muſt bee done,</l>
               <l>Of Idleneſſe comes nought but Ignorance:</l>
               <l>The Ditchers daughters and the Hedgers ſonne,</l>
               <l>Muſt make no marriage at a Morris daunce:</l>
               <l>But if that ſhee can ſowe, and he can reape,</l>
               <l>The Ric may hap to make a prety heape.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But to the purpoſe: What ſhall we goe doe?</l>
               <l>Make loue, and learne to tell a lye by Art:</l>
               <l>Oh no, it is an idle thing to wooe,</l>
               <l>And, on an eye to throw away a hart:</l>
               <l>It ſhewes, the braine lyes ill within the head,</l>
               <l>That workes all day to bring a foole to bed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet, let vs thinke on ſomething for our good,</l>
               <l>The world proteſteth againſt Idleneſſe:</l>
               <l>The Cuckowe findes a meanes to hatch her broode,</l>
               <l>Although ſhee cheate the Sparrowes ſimpleneſſe.</l>
               <l>But, ſince that Nature ſo her courſe hath runne,</l>
               <l>It is no matter, it muſt needes be done.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By laughing, now there is but little got:</l>
               <l>Ieſters and Iuglers may goe walke the Fayre:</l>
               <l>Beggers are lookt at, as men knew them not,</l>
               <l>The yonger brother ſeldome prooues the heyre,</l>
               <l>And yet ſometimes it doth vnhapply hit:</l>
               <l>The heyre a foole, the yonger hath the wit,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:7"/>
               <l>What ſhall wee then? turne fooles when all is done;</l>
               <l>Laugh, weare long coates, and ſing, and eate far meate:</l>
               <l>Follow my Maſter, dandle his young ſonne,</l>
               <l>And tell my Miſtreſſe, who the foole did beate,</l>
               <l>That ſhee may chide her wenches euery one,</l>
               <l>For medling with her foole, when ſhee was gone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or, ſhall we turne braue Pirats? ſcoure the Seas,</l>
               <l>And robbe, and kill, and drowne, or hang at laſt:</l>
               <l>Oh no, that courſe doth not mine humour pleaſe,</l>
               <l>Of all conceites, I like no halter caſt:</l>
               <l>For in the end, this fortune followes them,</l>
               <l>The Sea, the Gallowes, or hell ſwallowes them.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What ſhall wee then doe? ſpeake once like a Dogge,</l>
               <l>Shall wee turne Poets? proue Satiricall?</l>
               <l>And call an Aſſe, an Aſſe, a Hogge, a Hogge?</l>
               <l>Say holla, horſe, and to a Iade, ho Ball:</l>
               <l>Be libell knaues, and fooles vnto their faces.</l>
               <l>Oh no, I loue no pleading in ſuch caſes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What? ſhall we then turne Brokers, Vſurers?</l>
               <l>And ſtrippe the needy to their naked skinnes,</l>
               <l>Or ſecret B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibers, or Extortioners?</l>
               <l>Oh no, God bleſſe vs from ſuch diueliſh ſinnes.</l>
               <l>What? ſhall wee then bee Colliers? digge for Coles?</l>
               <l>Oh no, great dangers are in durty holes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:7"/>
               <l>What ſhall wee then doe? vve muſt not bee idle;</l>
               <l>Goe teach a Spaniell, how to fetch a Ducke:</l>
               <l>Or how to ride a Colte without a bridle,</l>
               <l>Or a young Nurſe, to giue a Baby ſucke?</l>
               <l>Oh no, theſe are but idle toyes and trifles,</l>
               <l>And there is nothing to be got with Nifles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Write Epitaphes vpon the death of dogges?</l>
               <l>And ſay, here lyes a good olde ſucking Curre;</l>
               <l>Cut ruſty faces out of rotten logges:</l>
               <l>And of an Owles skinne, make an Ape a furre?</l>
               <l>Or teach a Birde to whiſtle in a Cage.</l>
               <l>Or beare a Bride Cuppe at a marriage?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or ſing new Ballads? or make country games;</l>
               <l>Or ſet vp ſights were neuer ſeene before?</l>
               <l>Make Epigrams or Anagrams of names;</l>
               <l>Or learne the healing of a feſtred ſore?</l>
               <l>Learne any practiſe that may gather pelfe:</l>
               <l>But if thou loue me, doe not hang thy ſelfe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bring vp a Cat to hunt a Mouſe drie foote,</l>
               <l>Or teach a Squirrell how to clime a reede,</l>
               <l>A Skarre crow in a garden how to ſhoote,</l>
               <l>Or a blinde Harper; how a ſong to reade:</l>
               <l>Or how a flea may ſcape the fingers ends,</l>
               <l>Or how a lowſe may l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> among his friends.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:8"/>
               <l>But, canſt thou do no good with cats and dogs?</l>
               <l>Turne Ratcatcher, and lay for rats and mice:</l>
               <l>For, tis but idle to goe fiſh for frogs,</l>
               <l>And beggars get but little by their lice:</l>
               <l>And Pandariſme is ſo poore a trade,</l>
               <l>That none but beggers bargaine for a Iade.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But, doe not bite ſo ſoftly, make them ſmart,</l>
               <l>Tell Iohn a Noddes he is no Gentleman:</l>
               <l>And giue the Rogue the whippe, the Whore the cart,</l>
               <l>And turne the foole to his Maide Marian:</l>
               <l>And tell the Hobby horſe he is an Aſſe,</l>
               <l>And old Tom Piper but an Owliglaſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And tell the Wittoll, that doth weare the horne,</l>
               <l>Hee is a Raſcall, bee he neere ſo rich.</l>
               <l>And Iilian Iuſtice in her proudeſt ſcorne,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iane Shore</hi> her ſiſter, dyed but in a ditch:</l>
               <l>And Iacke a Lent that lookes aboue the Moone,</l>
               <l>His breakefaſt hath beene brought him after noone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell Tom a Lin, that holdes the world with tales,</l>
               <l>A Ieſter, and a Iacke, are coſen Iarmines:</l>
               <l>And he that trades for nuts, muſt take the ſhales:</l>
               <l>And Coney-keepers muſt lay trappes for vermines:</l>
               <l>And hee that goes a fiſhing for a Flooke,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> bee doe not looſe his hooke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:8"/>
               <l>And when the painted Image of ill thought,</l>
               <l>Shall ſee how Age ſhall ſhriuell vp her skinne,</l>
               <l>And ſhee ſhall ſee her cunning come to nought:</l>
               <l>When nature was but nouriſht vp with ſinne:</l>
               <l>Oh, in what fright will her poore ſpirit dwell,</l>
               <l>When ſhee ſhall ſerue for Kitchin ſtuffe in hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when the Bawde that fils the golden bagges,</l>
               <l>But with the fruit of Natures excrements,</l>
               <l>Shall at her death behold thoſe rotten ragges,</l>
               <l>That ſhall become her richeſt ornaments,</l>
               <l>How will her ſpirits fret, and ban and curſe,</l>
               <l>When ſhee ſhall ſerue to be the Diuels nurſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſo good Dogge, lie downe and take thy reſt,</l>
               <l>The beggers all are going home to bed:</l>
               <l>Each little birde is nuzling in her neſt:</l>
               <l>And euery horn'd beaſt ginnes to caſt the head,</l>
               <l>And euery Mowſe into her hoſe is gone,</l>
               <l>And thou haſt little left to thinke vpon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For if it bee, as I doe hope it is,</l>
               <l>The world is come vnto a happy paſſe:</l>
               <l>Kindneſſe lets no man know what thing is his:</l>
               <l>The Horſe is growne ſo inward with the Aſſe,</l>
               <l>And loue is growne ſo g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> friend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:9"/>
               <l>The coaſt is cleare, there are no knaues abroad,</l>
               <l>The Cuckowe huſht, and cannot ſing a note:</l>
               <l>The Owle is hid within the Iuy todde,</l>
               <l>And Iacke a Lent hath caſt his liuely cote,</l>
               <l>The Miller gone to the Market with his Mare,</l>
               <l>And cleanely wenches quickly ſell their hayre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There is no ſwearing now, but yea and nay,</l>
               <l>And Conſcience now determines euery caſe:</l>
               <l>And charity is ſo in euery way,</l>
               <l>That euery Begger dare to ſhew his face:</l>
               <l>And beauty is ſo courteous, and ſo kinde:</l>
               <l>That euery man for money knowes her mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And honeſty is wondrouſly beloued;</l>
               <l>And ſimple Truth is helde a bleſſed ſoule,</l>
               <l>And patience almoſt euery where approued.</l>
               <l>And vertue writ vp in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nly rowle,</l>
               <l>And Time ſo well imployde to profites vſe,</l>
               <l>That where no fault is; there needes no excuſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The rich men loue to heare the poore mens prayers,</l>
               <l>And poore men loue to take the ric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ens p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce:</l>
               <l>The wiſe and learned ſit in iudgements chaires</l>
               <l>And thiefes and murtherers hangs for their offence,</l>
               <l>And men and vvomen do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:9"/>
               <l>Tell William VVoodcocke with his winking eyes,</l>
               <l>Hee is a foole for all his ſhew of wit:</l>
               <l>And Lawrence Lobcocke, that he prates and lies</l>
               <l>Of his pied Beagle, and his Sorell Titte:</l>
               <l>And Dauid Dogbolt, with his boaſting brags,</l>
               <l>The Hangman is his Tayler for his Ragges.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell Peter Pudding; with his paltry ſtuffe,</l>
               <l>His wealth is all but in a Pedlers packe:</l>
               <l>And Saunder Huffe cappe, with his Ruffe and Snuffe,</l>
               <l>The Tinkers boy is but a bragging Iacke,</l>
               <l>And Sinior Spruſe that ſmoothes it like a Bride,</l>
               <l>He makes himſelfe the laughing ſtocke of pride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell Captaine To ſpot with his Tarletons cut,</l>
               <l>His ſwaggering will not get him ſixeteene pence:</l>
               <l>And Suſan Slapſauce ſhee is but a ſlut:</l>
               <l>For all her powder of experience,</l>
               <l>And Stabbing Stinckard with his minſing mouſe,</l>
               <l>The Hangman meetes him at the Seſſions houſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell Sloueniſta that doth lie and ſleepe.</l>
               <l>Hee breedes but filthy blood to fatten fleas:</l>
               <l>And drunken Dicke that layes his braines in ſteepe,</l>
               <l>The dropſie is a horrible diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>And Barnaby that goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>awdy Squire,</l>
               <l>A cuppe of ſacke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Noſe on fire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:10"/>
               <l>Tell Ragge a Muffin that doth rap out oathes,</l>
               <l>The Cutpurſe ſweares to keepe him company:</l>
               <l>When Tiburne ſhall vncaſe them of their clothes,</l>
               <l>And make an end of all their villany,</l>
               <l>While olde Madge Howlat, and yong Mawkin Spooner</l>
               <l>Will weepe for ſorrow, they were hangde no ſooner.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And tell olde Gregory with his grumbling chappes,</l>
               <l>Hee ſhall not beare a penny to his graue:</l>
               <l>And if hee doe not, looke to after claps:</l>
               <l>Hee may happe know, what tis to be a knaue:</l>
               <l>When hee ſhall lie in deadly gripes and grones,</l>
               <l>To ſee the diuell come to gnavv his bones.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And tell fine princking Parnell of Pickt hatch,</l>
               <l>The Surgeon ſayes, that ſhe is paſt all cure:</l>
               <l>And though ſhee couſned a poore ſilly patch,</l>
               <l>To bring a buzard to a baudy lure:</l>
               <l>Yet now, both towne and country knowes her trickes,</l>
               <l>Shee may goe ſeeke the hedge for rotten ſtickes,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And tell olde <hi>Tibbe,</hi> that dwells in Turnhole ſtreet,</l>
               <l>Her name hath beene in Bridewell long agoe;</l>
               <l>And for her breath it is ſo pockie ſweet,</l>
               <l>That all her teeth are rotten on a roe:</l>
               <l>And for her tongue the Clarke of Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ken well,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſhall bee ſent for, for chiefe ſcol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:10"/>
               <l>And tell that ilfac't whore of Iſlington,</l>
               <l>Shee poyſons all that come but neere her breath,</l>
               <l>And brings a world vnto confuſion:</l>
               <l>For, who comes neere her, comes vpon his death,</l>
               <l>And if he ſcape the plague the poxe will haue him,</l>
               <l>And if the diuell take him who ſhall ſaue him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell ſhame fac't ſheepes head with his rubies bluſh,</l>
               <l>He cannot make a curtſie handſomely:</l>
               <l>And, all his Rethoricke is not worth a Ruſh,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he tels his tale ill-fauouredly:</l>
               <l>And, for his miſtreſſe, ſhe can not abide him,</l>
               <l>Becauſe ſhe ſees the foole ſo often ride him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And, tell the Pander that doth purchaſe lands,</l>
               <l>Out of the luſt of filthy lechery;</l>
               <l>When, he ſhall fall into the Deuils hands:</l>
               <l>To feele the venome of loues trecherie:</l>
               <l>Beſmearde all with the excrements of nature:</l>
               <l>Hee ſhall in hell, be the moſt horride creature.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And tell the Lecher that doth take delight,</l>
               <l>To ferret all day at a Coneyhole:</l>
               <l>And makes the night his day, the day his night,</l>
               <l>When lacke of warmth ſhall make him blow the cole,</l>
               <l>After the poxe hath heere confounde his bones:</l>
               <l>His ſoule ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ones.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:11"/>
               <l>Tell Clownifiſta with his clowted ſhoes,</l>
               <l>His cobling craft will proue him but a knaue,</l>
               <l>VVhen that his noſe is in the Deuils nooſe,</l>
               <l>His ſoule in hell ſhall ſerue but for a ſlaue,</l>
               <l>Within the ſincke of all the filth of ſinne,</l>
               <l>To dig vp holes to throw the damned in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And tell the ouerglutted Epicure,</l>
               <l>Whoſe eaſe delighteth but in fat and froth,</l>
               <l>When he in hell ſhall hourely toyle endure,</l>
               <l>And haue his wages in vnwholeſome broth.</l>
               <l>When boyling leade ſhall doe his guts no good,</l>
               <l>When hee ſhall ſtarue or gnawe his fleſh for food.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Be ſullen, loure, and skowle at knaues, and fooles,</l>
               <l>That walking come by thee like men of worth:</l>
               <l>And ſend the ſcoldes vnto the cucking ſtooles:</l>
               <l>And bring the beggers with their wallets foorth:</l>
               <l>And ſweepe the ſtreetes from all the cheating mates,</l>
               <l>And take heed of the horne beaſts in the gates.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Runne all about among the raſcall people,</l>
               <l>And beat the beggers from the rich mens doores,</l>
               <l>And goe from Charing Croſſe vnto <hi>Paules</hi> ſteeple,</l>
               <l>And clenſe the ſtreetes of all the knaues and whores,</l>
               <l>Kill all the dogges for feare of their faction,</l>
               <l>And ſend the idle roagues vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rection.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:11"/>
               <l>Scoure all the coaſts, Kent ſtreet and Clarken well,</l>
               <l>Wapping, Eaſt Smithfield, Chick lane &amp; Turnhole ſtreet</l>
               <l>Pickthatche, the Spittle, Shorditch, and Halliwell;</l>
               <l>And all the by-lanes where the Baudes doe meet:</l>
               <l>And Tuttill ſtreet, S. Giles and Iſlington:</l>
               <l>And make a ſteppe ouer to Newington,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All ſcolding Allies, and ſuch ſcuruey places;</l>
               <l>And take them as thou find'ſt them euery where:</l>
               <l>Bring out the Punkes with all their pockie faces,</l>
               <l>The purple, tawnie, round and ruſſer haire,</l>
               <l>Set vp a ſtake, and bring rhe Refuſe thether,</l>
               <l>And make a Bonefire of them all together.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Make much of none, but true kind hearted wenches,</l>
               <l>That would be honeſt, if they could tell how,</l>
               <l>But meddle with no great ones on their benches,</l>
               <l>For feare of worſe hurt then a broken brow:</l>
               <l>Yet if thou ſee'ſt a knacke of knauery goe</l>
               <l>Thinke what thou liſt, although thou ſay not ſo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Barke at a Traytor, ſawne not on a theefe,</l>
               <l>Tell them the halter hangs right in their way:</l>
               <l>And tell rhe Butcher when hee buyes his beefe,</l>
               <l>The hornes may helpe to make the hide away,</l>
               <l>And watch the leaſt good fortune may befall,</l>
               <l>For greedy hounds will haue the deuill and all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:12"/>
               <l>Or, with <hi>Diogenes,</hi> goe ſeeke and ſee,</l>
               <l>If by a Lanthorne, and a Candle light:</l>
               <l>Thou canſt finde out where there may hidden be:</l>
               <l>One honeſt man from wicked wordlings ſight:</l>
               <l>Or make a Suruey of old <hi>Timons</hi> trees:</l>
               <l>Whether the pockie vvhores haue payde their fees.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Rayle at the world, and hate it to the death,</l>
               <l>And ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y it is but patience Purgatory:</l>
               <l>A c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>red mouth that giues a curſed breath:</l>
               <l>That ſounds but ſorrow, death, and miſery:</l>
               <l>Where he that can in his beſt ſence conceiue it:</l>
               <l>Thinkes himſelfe neuer happy, till hee leaue it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But for the vertuous, eyther high or low:</l>
               <l>Honour and loue them, though thou doſt not know the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</l>
               <l>But for the vitious, let the villaines goe:</l>
               <l>Downe to the hell, a blaſt of whirlewinde blow them:</l>
               <l>Yet vviſh them not to hell, but ſomewhat better:</l>
               <l>Although thou knoweſt they be the Hangmans debter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fret till the fleſh bee bare vnto the bones,</l>
               <l>To ſee thy ſpirit ſo thy body ſpend:</l>
               <l>Sigh, ſob, and ſwell, with ſuch deepe inward grones,</l>
               <l>As heart would burſt, to ſee thou canſt not mend:</l>
               <l>Not mend a ſlender hurt, nor little paine:</l>
               <l>But heart all broke, that cannot heale againe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:12"/>
               <l>Bite hard thy lippes, and ſhake thy troubled head,</l>
               <l>And grate thy teeth vntill thy gummes doe bleede:</l>
               <l>And looke as lumpiſh as a peece of lead,</l>
               <l>And ſpeake to no man, but to ſerue thy neede,</l>
               <l>Walke by thy ſelfe, and ſeeke no company,</l>
               <l>And hate the thought of helliſh villanie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For, let rich <hi>Midas</hi> bee a golden aſſe,</l>
               <l>And like a toade, a dogged tyrant ſwell:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Iudas</hi> with his poyſoned ſpirit paſſe,</l>
               <l>With all the curſed damned crue to hell:</l>
               <l>Loue thou thy God, and for the godly pray:</l>
               <l>And ſo, with all the world make holy day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If that thou ſee a Begger grow to wealth,</l>
               <l>Marke how he gets it, and ſo giue him grace:</l>
               <l>If honeſtly, regarde him, if by ſtealth</l>
               <l>Of villany, wiſh him a viler place,</l>
               <l>And yet alas, in charitie pray for him:</l>
               <l>Hell may not haue him, though the heauens abhor hin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And put on patience, for it is but vaine</l>
               <l>To fret and fume, and chafe, and play the foole:</l>
               <l>Let vs goe fall vpon ſome finer ſtraine,</l>
               <l>And bring our wits vnto ſome better ſchoole:</l>
               <l>Entreat a little, it may breed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good blood,</l>
               <l>See if fayre words will I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the world to good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:13"/>
               <l>Entreat all knaues to turne, all honeſt men,</l>
               <l>And honeſt men they will be honeſt ſtill:</l>
               <l>Entreat no Cocke to treade his neighbours henne:</l>
               <l>But let the Turtles kindly ſit and bill:</l>
               <l>Entreat the Tinker, better ſtop his holes,</l>
               <l>And Grim the Colier giue vs better coles,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Entreat the ſhepheard that doth ſheare his ſheepe,</l>
               <l>Hee will not clip too low, to cut the skinne:</l>
               <l>And bid his woman that ſhee doe not weepe,</l>
               <l>Becauſe the mouſe hath beene within her Binne:</l>
               <l>Her husband will not feele it in his purſe,</l>
               <l>And ſift the meale, the bread is neere the worſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Entreat the Geeſe and Ganders hold their peace,</l>
               <l>There is not one wiſe word among them all:</l>
               <l>And all the alley ſcoldes, their brawling ceaſe,</l>
               <l>For tis a filthy thing to ſcolde and brawle:</l>
               <l>And all fayre wenches that are beauties flowrse,</l>
               <l>They will not be the Deuils Paramours.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Intreat the Aſſes for to leaue their braying,</l>
               <l>The Peacocke that he will not ſtoupe his tayle:</l>
               <l>And mad young wenches for to leaue their maying:</l>
               <l>The milke mayde that ſhee looke vnto her payle:</l>
               <l>The Stallion horſe, hee doe not beat the mare,</l>
               <l>And greedy houndes they doe not kill the hare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Now fie on fooles cap, heere's a diſh of drinke,</l>
               <l>To choke a dogge, let all theſe toyes alone:</l>
               <l>Let vs our ſelues of ſomewhat elſe bethinke,</l>
               <l>That yet may doe ſome good when all is gone:</l>
               <l>That though our bodies our of frame are growne,</l>
               <l>Our ſpirits yet may not be ouerthrowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then let vs leaue the world and go to Church,</l>
               <l>And turne all Preachers true and holy men?</l>
               <l>And while the Knaue doth giue the foole the lurch.</l>
               <l>And plotters write, with an vngodly penne:</l>
               <l>Let vs deliuer by the word of truth,</l>
               <l>The way to heauen, both vnto age and youth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yea, let vs reade the rules of ſacred life,</l>
               <l>Perſwade the troubled ſoule to patience:</l>
               <l>The husbands care, and comfort to the wife:</l>
               <l>The childe and ſeruant, due obedience,</l>
               <l>Faith to the friend, and to the neighbour peace,</l>
               <l>That loue may liue, and ſuites at law may ceaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pray for the health of all that are diſeaſed,</l>
               <l>Confeſſion vnto all that are conuicted:</l>
               <l>And patience vnto all that are diſpleaſed,</l>
               <l>And comfort vnto all that are afflicted,</l>
               <l>And mercy vnto all that haue offended,</l>
               <l>And Grace to all, that all may be amended,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:14"/>
               <l>Pray for the King, the Queene, and Countries health,</l>
               <l>Their royall Iſſue, and their Peeres of State:</l>
               <l>The Councell, Clergy, and the common wealth,</l>
               <l>That no misfortune may their bliſſe abate.</l>
               <l>But that th'almighty ſo his Church will cheriſh,</l>
               <l>That not a member of his loue may periſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To King and Queene giue Rights of Royalty,</l>
               <l>And for their vertues giue them worthy prayſe:</l>
               <l>Grace to the Prince, the Subiect loyalty,</l>
               <l>That all together may haue happy dayes,</l>
               <l>The Councell wiſdome, and the Commons wealth,</l>
               <l>The vertuous honour, and the gracious health.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Inuay againſt all vile iniquity,</l>
               <l>But chide the ſinner with no bitter checke:</l>
               <l>But ſo perſwade him with ſuch piety,</l>
               <l>That on the blocke hee may lay downe his necke,</l>
               <l>And at the ſtroke of death ſuch comfort finde,</l>
               <l>As mercy giues to a repentant mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Come by the proude with, Lucifers great fall,</l>
               <l>And lay downe <hi>Dinah</hi> at the vnchaſt dore,</l>
               <l>The irreligious with the life of <hi>Paul,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who once conuerted, neuer fell no more,</l>
               <l>The painted face with wicked <hi>Iezabel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And the rich Churle with <hi>Diues</hi> deepe in hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Come by the fine, but fond conceited wit,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Herods</hi> and in all his Eloquence:</l>
               <l>And tell the franticke in a furious fit,</l>
               <l>Of curſed <hi>Saul,</hi> in his impatience,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Ananiah,</hi> touch ill conſcience,</l>
               <l>And bribing hands with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thirty pence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Come by the Iudge that giues Iniuſtice doome,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Pilats</hi> feare of <hi>Ceſar,</hi> more then God:</l>
               <l>And bid the Tyrant looke on <hi>Neroes</hi> toombe,</l>
               <l>Whoſe fleſh an earth with wormes doth make abode:</l>
               <l>While deepe in hell, his ſoule doth feele the ſmart</l>
               <l>Of a proud Tirants bloody wicked hart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell them that murmure at heauens Maieſty,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abirams</hi> death:</l>
               <l>And finely touch the tongue of blaſphemie,</l>
               <l>With huge <hi>Goliah</hi> in his helliſh breath:</l>
               <l>And bid the murtherer looke on <hi>Abels</hi> blood,</l>
               <l>When teares nor prayers, <hi>Caine</hi> did any good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And tell the powerfull in their higheſt places,</l>
               <l>That mercy is the grace of maieſty:</l>
               <l>And from the poore the proud that turne their faces,</l>
               <l>Shall finde the fruits of their Impiety.</l>
               <l>When deafened helliſh eares, and blinded eyes,</l>
               <l>Will ſee no teares, nor heare the damned cries</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:15"/>
               <l>Allure the world to charitable loue,</l>
               <l>And ſhew the comfort of a chriſtian peace:</l>
               <l>And ſeeke the ſweetneſſe in the ſoule to proue:</l>
               <l>How patience, vertue makes all paſſions ceaſe,</l>
               <l>In humble, faithfull, carefull, conſtant, kinde,</l>
               <l>Set downe the notes of a true noble mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bid virgins follow all the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And men their Maſter Chriſt in all his merits:</l>
               <l>And men and women all their ſelues ſo carry,</l>
               <l>That they may ſhew true hearts and chriſtian ſpirits,</l>
               <l>In mildeneſſe, meekeneſſe, and loues lowlineſſe,</l>
               <l>Set dovvne the notes of natures happineſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Giue beauty warning of a wanton eye,</l>
               <l>And riches warning of a wretched mind:</l>
               <l>And Honour warning of Indignity,</l>
               <l>And aged eyes from being Cupid blinde:</l>
               <l>And power a warning of the fall of pride.</l>
               <l>And pray, the gracious may in grace abide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſhew the curſes threatned vpon ſinne,</l>
               <l>The bleſſings on obedience vnto grace:</l>
               <l>And how the curſed here their hell beginne,</l>
               <l>Whoſe teares nor prayers in mercy haue no place:</l>
               <l>And how the bleſſed heere beginne to taſt</l>
               <l>The ioyes of heauen that ſhall for euer laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:15"/>
               <l>Wiſh euery King to haue King <hi>Dauids</hi> heart,</l>
               <l>And euery Queene, the Queen of Sheb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s wit:</l>
               <l>And euery Councell, <hi>Salomons</hi> beſt part</l>
               <l>Of vnderſtanding, for a kingdome ſitte,</l>
               <l>And euery Lady, fayre <hi>Rebecca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> face,</l>
               <l>And euery Virgin, the wiſe Virgins grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And euery Souldier, <hi>Ioſuahs</hi> true ſpirit,</l>
               <l>And euery Scholer <hi>Aarons</hi> Eloquence,</l>
               <l>And euery Miſer, wicked <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> merit:</l>
               <l>And euery poore man <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> true patience,</l>
               <l>And euery Lawyer <hi>Moſes</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nly mind</l>
               <l>And euery Marchant of <hi>Zac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> kind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Doe not with <hi>Eſau</hi> him of or Veniſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>And ſell thy birthright for a meſſe of po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge:</l>
               <l>Leſt <hi>Iacob</hi> ſteale away thy B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>on.</l>
               <l>When <hi>Iſaac</hi> fals vpon the yeeres of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>otag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</l>
               <l>But be a <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in the time of heed</l>
               <l>To good olde <hi>Iacob,</hi> and his bleſſed ſeed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Be <hi>Abraham</hi> in his ſonnes ſacrifice,</l>
               <l>And follow <hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in his loues h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lineſſe,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Salomon</hi> be in thy iudgement wiſe,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Ionathan</hi> in friendſhip faithfulneſſe,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Henoch</hi> make thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> loue;</l>
               <l>And with <hi>Eliah</hi> liue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:16"/>
               <l>Be both a Prieſt, a Prophet and a King,</l>
               <l>A Prieſt to make thy heart a Sacrifice,</l>
               <l>A Prophet to declare the way to bring</l>
               <l>The bleſſed Spirit vnto Paradiſe,</l>
               <l>A King to rule thy ſelfe with ſuch direction,</l>
               <l>Thy ſoule may keepe thy body in ſubiection.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh kill not Conſcience with a cruell letter,</l>
               <l>Yet let the Atheiſt haue but little hope</l>
               <l>And count the falſe Profeſſor little be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er,</l>
               <l>That for diſſembling doth deſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> the rope,</l>
               <l>For cleanely Cook<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> doe more it is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>th,</l>
               <l>That filthy water makes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And make no monſter member of the Church,</l>
               <l>Nor take ill counſell of <hi>Achitophel:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor let illuſion giue thy ſoule the lurch,</l>
               <l>To leade thy heart into the ſinke of hell,</l>
               <l>Teach humble loue, hate all ambition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pride,</l>
               <l>And ſhrowde thy vertues vnder Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And diet not with <hi>Holofor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> drinke,</l>
               <l>But ioyne with <hi>Iudith</hi> in her ioyfull ſtrength,</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Dalila,</hi> not make ſtout <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mpſon</hi> winke,</l>
               <l>Leſt the Philiſtints fall on thee at length,</l>
               <l>No <hi>Salomon</hi> be led by <hi>Phara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt by the fleſh, the ſpirit be b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>lde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Know, what and when, and where, and how to ſpeake</l>
               <l>Bee fearefull, how thou doeſt thy God offend:</l>
               <l>A vertuous vow, take heede thou doeſt not breake,</l>
               <l>And Mercies pleaſure, patiently a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Loue no man for his purſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for his place:</l>
               <l>But for his wit, his vertue and his grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Be wiſely carefull, but not couetous,</l>
               <l>For Conſcience wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, will make a mortall wound,</l>
               <l>And be deuout, but not Idolatrous:</l>
               <l>For, that both ſoule and body will confound:</l>
               <l>Be kindly louing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> lecherous,</l>
               <l>For that in, nature is moſt impious,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To idle things accuſtome not thy thought:</l>
               <l>And tremble at the word of Blaſphemy:</l>
               <l>With vaine perſwaſions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> wrought,</l>
               <l>And keepe thy tongue from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Infamy;</l>
               <l>Hold backe thy hand from all vnlawfull action;</l>
               <l>And weane thy Spirit from vngodly faction.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Care not to reade except to underſtand,</l>
               <l>And let thy learning teach thee how to liue:</l>
               <l>With perfect care let euery courſe be ſcand;</l>
               <l>And ſpare to ſpend, that thou mayeſt haue to giue,</l>
               <l>Thinke no man happy o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Stage,</l>
               <l>Where death and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>; make a marriage</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:17"/>
               <l>Prie not into the faults of priu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>To lay them open to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eed ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>;</l>
               <l>Nor ſtrike a daſh with a falſe deadly pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</l>
               <l>To kill the credit of an honeſt na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e;</l>
               <l>And for the ſimple, vſe no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>btil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>But pitty the afflicted in their paines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Flatter not folly with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n idle faith,</l>
               <l>Nor let earth ſtand vpon her owne deſart;</l>
               <l>But ſhew what wiſdome in the ſcripture ſaith,</l>
               <l>The fruitfull hand doth ſhow the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>thful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art,</l>
               <l>Beleeue the Word, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nd thy will,</l>
               <l>And teach obedience for a bleſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let not the beauteous, nor the ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h be proud,</l>
               <l>Nor aged wanton, nor the youthfull wilde;</l>
               <l>For in the rules of Grace, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not allow'd,</l>
               <l>And graceles h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ts, are all from heauen e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ld:</l>
               <l>Let valour nor be cruell, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> kinde,</l>
               <l>Nor baſe conceits corrupt a no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But do not raue, nor raile, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or ſtare,</l>
               <l>As if thy care would go to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ffes with ſinne:</l>
               <l>But ſhew how mercy doth repentance ſpar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Whileſt working faith doth heau'nly fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our winne,</l>
               <l>And Loues obedience to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</l>
               <l>The choſen ſoule, that God doth chiefly loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:17"/>
               <l>Chide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inners, as the Father doth his childe,</l>
               <l>And keepe them in the awe of louing feare:</l>
               <l>Make ſinne moſt hatefull, but in words be nice,</l>
               <l>That humble patience may the better heare;</l>
               <l>And wounded conſcience may receyue reliefe,</l>
               <l>When true repentance pleade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſinners griefe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Throw not the ſinner headlong to damnation,</l>
               <l>Nor fright the faithfull with a curſed feare;</l>
               <l>But winne Repentance vnto Reformation,</l>
               <l>And teach the Chriſtian, how his croſſe to beare,</l>
               <l>Giue comfort in thy Cares inſtruction,</l>
               <l>To ſaue the faithfull from the ſoules deſtruction.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Heale the Infect of ſinne with oyle of grace,</l>
               <l>And waſh the ſoule with true contritions teares,</l>
               <l>And when Confeſſion ſhewes her heauy caſe,</l>
               <l>Deliuer faith from all Infernall feares,</l>
               <l>That when high Iuſtice threat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſinne with death,</l>
               <l>Mercy againe, may giue Repentance breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet flatter not the fowle delight of ſinne,</l>
               <l>But make it loathſome in the eye of loue;</l>
               <l>And ſeeke the heart with holy c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res to winne,</l>
               <l>To worke the beſt way for the ſoules be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue?</l>
               <l>So teach, ſo liue, that both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> deed,</l>
               <l>The would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10320:18"/>
               <l>Time hath a courſe, that Nature cannot ſtay,</l>
               <l>For youth muſt die, or come to doting age:</l>
               <l>What is our life on earth? but as a play,</l>
               <l>Where many a part doth come vpon the Stage,</l>
               <l>Rich, poore, wiſe, fond, fayre, fowle, and great, and ſmall</l>
               <l>And old, and young, death makes an end of all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where hee that makes his life a Comedy,</l>
               <l>To laugh and ſing, and talke away the Time:</l>
               <l>Shall finde it in the end a Tragedie,</l>
               <l>When mournefull bells, will make no merry chime,</l>
               <l>When ſad deſpayre ſhall feare infernall euill,</l>
               <l>While Sinne and death; are Agents for the Deuill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh when the rich, and greedy Miſer dies,</l>
               <l>While fearefull viſions will his ſoule affright?</l>
               <l>And keepe his heart in helliſh miſeries,</l>
               <l>To looke vpon ſo many a fearefull ſight,</l>
               <l>When Pride, oppreſſion, Auarice and Theft,</l>
               <l>Of hope, of mercy, hath the foule bereft.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when the Murtherer that delights in blood,</l>
               <l>Shall feele his heart to haue a mortall wound:</l>
               <l>And grieues to looke vpon ill gotten good,</l>
               <l>While guilty conſcience runnes his care a ground:</l>
               <l>What will hee doe? when truth his ſoule ſhall tell,</l>
               <l>A tyrants blood ſhall make a broth in hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10320:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
